Brian Libgober

School of Global Policy and Strategy University of California, San Diego blibgober@ucsd.edu +1 708 642 4741 brianlibgober.com

EDUCATION

Ph.D. Government, Harvard University, 2018

M.A. Statistics, Harvard University, 2017

J.D. University of Michigan Law School, cum laude, 2015

B.A. Mathematics and Philosophy, University of Chicago, with honors, 2010

APPOINTMENTS

2020 – University of California, San Diego

Assistant Professor, School of Global Policy and Strategy

2018–20 Yale University

Postdoctoral Associate, Department of Political Science

RESEARCH SUMMARY

I research the political economy of American institutions, with a particular emphasis on regulation-making by executive agencies. The majority of American political scientists working on regulation focus on issues of separation of powers, political control, and oversight. By contrast, my work attends to issues of distribution and the often fraught relationship between regulators and lobbyists. More broadly, I explore themes of economic inequality, interest group power, and the design of legal and governmental institutions. Methodologically, I combine multiple approaches, including formal models, quantitative empirics, and case studies.

PUBLICATIONS

Peer-Reviewed Journal Articles

"Strategic Proposals, Endogenous Comments, and Bias in Rulemaking." *The Journal of Politics*. DOI: 10.1086/706891. Brian Libgober.

"Meetings, Comments, and the Distributive Politics of Rulemaking." *Quarterly Journal of Political Science*. DOI: 10.1561/100.00018135. Brian Libgober.

"Data and Methods for Analyzing Special Interest Influence in Rulemaking." *Interest Groups Ed Advocacy*. DOI: 10.1057/s41309-020-00094-w. Daniel P. Carpenter, Devin Judge-Lord, Brian Libgober, and Steven Rashin.

Working Papers[†]

- "Lawyers as Lobbyists." Daniel P. Carpenter and Brian Libgober.
- "Making Regulators Reasonable: Do Procedural Rationality Requirements Fix Cognitive Biases?" Benjamin Minhao Chen and Brian Libgober.
- "Personnel, Politics, and the Trump Presidency." Brian Libgober and Mark D. Richardson.
- "The Political Ideologies of Organized Interests & Amicus Curiae Briefs: Large-Scale, Social Network Imputation of Ideal Points." Sahar Abi-Hassan, Janet M. Box-Steffensmeier, Dino P. Christenson, Aaron R. Kaufman, and Brian Libgober.
- "Linking Datasets on Organizations Using Half A Billion Open Collaborated Records."

 Connor Jerzak and Brian Libgober.
- 2020 "Agency Failure and Individual Accountability." Brian Libgober.
- "An Email Experiment to Identify the Effect of Racial Discrimination on Access to Lawyers: A Statistical Approach." arXiv: 1908.08116. Brian Libgober and Tirthankar Dasgupta.

Work In Progress

- "Ex Post Lobbying and the Dynamics of Legislative Attention." Brian Libgober.
- "Participatory Inequality and Rulemaking: Evidence from Financial Regulation."

 Brian Libgober, Susan Webb Yackee, Daniel P. Carpenter, Steven Rashin, Devin Judge-Lord, Jacob Waggoner, and Chris Kenny.
- "Lobbying, Cheap Talk, and Norms of Aggregation." Chris Li and Brian Libgober.
- "The Politics of Place: Evidence from Refugees to the United States." Valentin Bolotnyy, Mayya Komisarchik, and Brian Libgober.

Other Publications

- In Press "High-Traceability Administrative Politics: Strategic Commenting upon Federal Reserve Debit Card Regulations." Daniel P. Carpenter and Brian Libgober.
- "Getting a Lawyer While Black: A Field Experiment." Lewis & Clark Law Review. DOI: 10.2139/ssrn.3389279. Brian Libgober.
- "Lobbying the Rulemakers with Lawyers: Reflections from the Volcker Rule." *Extensions*. Daniel P. Carpenter and Brian Libgober.
- "Can the EU be a Constitutional System Without Universal Access to Judical Review?"

 Michigan Journal of International Law. Brian Libgober.

INVITED TALKS

- Georgetown University. Department of Government. "Agency Failure and Individual Accountability," Jan 24.
- University of Texas, Austin. McCombs School of Business. "Meetings, Comments, and the Distributive Politics of Administrative Policymaking," Jan 8.

[†]Drafts of all working papers are available at https://brianlibgober.com.

- Stanford University. Hoover Institution. "Meetings, Comments, and the Distributive Politics of Administrative Policymaking," Dec 6.
- Vanderbilt University. Department of Political Science. "Meetings, Comments, and the Distributive Politics of Administrative Policymaking," Nov 13.
- University of California, San Diego. School of Global Policy and Strategy. "Meetings, Comments, and the Distributive Politics of Administrative Policymaking," Nov 6.
- 2019 Harvard Law School. "Meetings, Comments, and the Distributive Politics of Administrative Policymaking," Nov 5.
- George Mason Law School. "Agency Failure and Individual Accountability," Sep 19.
- Washington University in St. Louis. Department of Political Science. "Meetings, Comments, and the Distributive Politics of Administrative Policymaking," Sep 17.
- Berkeley Law School. Jurisprudence and Social Policy Program. "Meetings, Comments, and the Distributive Politics of Administrative Policymaking," Feb 7.
- Harvard Business School. Business Government and International Economy Unit. "Meetings, Comments, and the Distributive Politics of Administrative Policymaking," Nov 5.
- Administrative Conference of the United States. "The Gains from Lobbying Financial Regulators," Aug 9.
- University of Texas, Austin. McCombs School of Business. "What's at Stake in Rulemaking? Financial Market Evidence for Banks' Influence on Administrative Agencies," Mar 23.

CONFERENCE ACTIVITY

Conference Presentations

- American Political Science Association (APSA) Annual Conference. "The Politics of Place: Evidence from Refugees to the US," Oct 2.
- American Political Science Association (APSA) Annual Conference. "Ex Post Lobbying and the Dynamics of Legislative Attention," Oct 1.
- American Political Science Association (APSA) Annual Conference. "Participatory Inequality and Rulemaking: Evidence from Financial Regulation," Sep 30.
- American Political Economy Summer School. "Lawyers as Lobbyists," Jul 1.
- American Political Science Association (APSA) Annual Conference. "One Voice: the Role of Organization in Lobbying," Sep 10.
- Bureaucracy and Presidential Administration: Expertise and Accountability in Constitutional Government. George Mason Law School. "Agency Failure and Individual Accountability," Dec 6.
- American Law and Economics Association (ALEA) Annual Conference. "Meetings, Comments, and the Distributive Politics of Administrative Policymaking," May 17.
- Southern Political Science Association (SPSA) Annual Conference. "Meetings, Comments, and the Distributive Politics of Administrative Policymaking," Jan 18.
- 2018 Midwest Political Science Association (MPSA) Annual Conference. "What Public Comments During Rulemaking Do (and Why)," Apr 7.

- 2018 Midwest Political Science Association (MPSA) Annual Conference. "The Price of Votes," Apr 5.
- Southern Political Science Association (SPSA) Annual Conference. "What Public Comments During Rulemaking Do (and Why)," Jan 5.
- Southern Political Science Association (SPSA) Annual Conference. "Participation, Inequality, and Rational Responsiveness," Jan 4.
- Radcliffe Institute for Advanced Study. "Lobbying with Lawyers: Financial Market Evidence for Banks' Influence on Rulemaking," Dec 8.
- Midwest Political Science Association (MPSA) Annual Conference. "Equities and Inequities in Financial Rulemaking," Apr 6.
- University of Chicago Booth Business School. "Lawyering and Lobbying: Why Banks Shape Rules," Mar 4.
- American Law and Economics Association (ALEA) Annual Meeting. "Accident Liability in Imperfectly Competitive Markets," May 16.

Poster Sessions

Annual Conference on Empirical Legal Studies (CELS). "Meetings, Comments, and the Distributive Politics of Administrative Policymaking," Nov 9.

Other Conference Participation

- American Political Science Association (APSA) Annual Conference. "Lobbyists and Lobbying, Strategies and Goals," Oct 3 (discussant).
- American Political Science Association (APSA) Annual Conference. "Politics of Rulemaking in the Administration State," Oct 1 (discussant).
- American Political Science Association (APSA) Annual Conference. "Legislative Productivity in the US," Sep 29 (chair and discussant).
- American Political Science Association (APSA) Annual Conference. "Separation of Powers and Interbranch Relationships," Sep 30 (chair and discussant).
- American Political Science Association (APSA) Annual Conference. "Advances in Law Enforcement Policy Research," Sep 30 (chair).

DEPARTMENTAL TALKS

- University of California, San Diego. School of Global Policy and Strategy Junior Faculty Brownbag. "Does Electoral Politics Explain the Distribution of CDC Test Kits? Evidence from FOIA," Oct 28.
- Harvard University. Political Economy Workshop. "Meetings, Comments, and the Distributive Politics of Administrative Policymaking," Oct 29.
- Harvard University. American Politics Research Workshop. "What Public Comments During Rulemaking Do (and Why)," Feb 13.
- Harvard University. Working Group in Political Psychology. "Getting a Lawyer While Black: A Field Experiment," Mar 10.

- Harvard University. American Politics Research Workshop. "Lawyering and Lobbying: Why Banks Shape Rules," Feb 7.
- Harvard University. Harvard Experiments Working Group. "Getting a Lawyer While Black: A Field Experiment," Sep 9.
- Harvard Law School. Law and Economics Seminar. "Getting a Lawyer While Black: A Field Experiment," Mar 3.

FELLOWSHIPS

- 2016-18 Stone PhD Scholar in Inequality and Wealth Concentration, Harvard Kennedy School.
- 2015 Terence M. Considine Fellowship in Law and Economics, Harvard Law School.
- 2012-15 Dean's Scholarship, University of Michigan Law School.
- 2006-10 Viola Bower Merit Scholarship, University of Chicago.

TEACHING

University of California San Diego

- 2021 Policy Analysis and Social Welfare (MPP/MIA). Primary Instructor. Fall.
- Law and Administration (MPP/MIA). Primary Instructor. Fall.
- Law and Administration (MPP/MIA). Primary Instructor. Spring.
- Bureaucratic Politics (MPP/MIA). Primary Instructor. Spring.
- 2021 Interest Groups and the Policymaking Process (MPP/MIA). Primary Instructor. Winter.

Yale University

- American Mass Media: Law, Politics, and Policy (Undergraduate). Primary Instructor. Fall.
- 2019 Money in Politics (MPP/MIA). Primary Instructor. Spring.

Harvard University

- Formal Models of Domestic Politics (PhD). Teaching Assistant (Primary Instructor: Horacio Larreguy). Fall.
- Bureaucratic Politics (Undergraduate/Graduate). Teaching Assistant (Primary Instructor: Daniel Carpenter). Fall.

Massachussets Institute of Technology

2015 Constitutional Law & Judicial Politics (PhD). Course Assistant (Primary Instructor: Chris Warshaw). Spring.

University of Michigan

Mass Media and Election Politics (Undergraduate). Graduate Student Instructor (Primary Instructor: Nicholas Valentino). Fall.

SERVICE TO THE FIELD

Academic Peer Review

American Political Science Review

JPART

The Journal of Politics

American Journal of Political Science

Politics & Gender

DEPARTMENTAL SERVICE

University of California San Diego

2021- Law and Policy Ad Hoc Exploratory Committee.

2020- Admission's Committee.

Harvard University

2015-17 Graduate Student Coordinator, Undergraduate Research Scholars Program, Institute for

Quantitative Social Science.

MEMBERSHIPS

American Political Science Association

Midwest Political Science Association

Southern Political Science Association

American Law and Economics Association

PROFESSIONAL EMPLOYMENT

Summer Law Clerk. UNC School of Government. Chapel Hill, North Carolina.

Summer Associate. Paul Hastings LLP. New York, NY.

Summer Law Clerk to Chief Judge Beryl Howell. US District Court. Washington, DC.

2011-12 Polling Analyst. Obama for America Reelection Campaign. Chicago, IL.

CONSULTING

2020 M4BL: The Movement for Black Lives. Advised on sections of the BREATHE ACT.

2019 Cleveland County, North Carolina. Advised on anti-subsidy doctrines in US Constitutional law.

Updated August 2021